George Fuermann "Texas and Houston" Collection
University of Houston Libraries
- I. George Fuermann Historical Collection, 1836-1988, 8 Series, (A - H)
  - G. Artifacts, 1891-1962, 12 Items
    - United Confederate Veteran's Reunion Ribbons., 1893-1895; 2 items (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Houston Transit Token., [undated]; 1 item (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Pendant Medals., 1891-1931; 3 items (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Button Pins., 1897-1916; 3 items (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - City of Houston Police Uniform Button., [undated]; 1 item (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Rim Fire [local co.] Rifle Cartridge Box., [undated]; 1 item (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Rice Institute Semi-Centennial Medallion., 1962; 1 item (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Prudential Bldg. Commemorative Medallion., 1952; 1 item (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - University of Houston belt buckle, 1934 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - World Globe, Desk Model, 1897 (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Antique Dictionary Stand, undated (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Large Decorative Serving Tray -- local beer advert, undated (Box OVS 10)
  - H. Research Files, 14 Boxes, 180 Folders
    These 14 boxes of research files contain a wealth of information consisting of clipped articles, obituaries, correspondence, photographs, ephemeral items and the signatures of such prominent local notable as Miss Ima Hogg, Mayor Oscar Holcombe and Jesse H. Jones. The series consists of 47 biographical files on local individuals and families, as well as 133 subject files on local organizations and entities.
    - Biographical Files
      - Abercrombie (James S.) Family (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - Allen Family (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - Anderson, M.D. (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Biggers, John (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - Blaffer (Robert L.) Family (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - Brown, George & Hermann (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - Clayton (W. L.) Family (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - Cleveland, Tony (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - Collins, Lowell (Box 26, Folder 9)
      - Cullen, Ezekial (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - Cullen, Hugh Roy (Box 26, Folder 11)
      - Cullinan (J.S.) Family (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - De Menil, John & Dominique (Box 26, Folder 13)
      - Dowling, Richard W. (Dick) (Box 26, Folder 14)
      - Heitmann, F.W. (Box 26, Folder 15)
      - Hermann, George (Box 26, Folder 16)
      - Hobby, Wm. P. Family (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - Hofheinz, Roy M. (Box 26, Folder 18)
      - Hogg, Ima (Box 26, Folder 19)
      - Hogg, Gov. James S. (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Hogg, Will (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - Hogg (J.S.) Family (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - Holcombe, Oscar (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Houstonians, Other 1 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - Houstonians, Other 2 (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - Jones, Jesse H. (Box 27, Folder 7)
      - Kellum, Nathaniel K (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - Kemp, Louis Wiltz (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - Kirby, John Henry (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - McCarthy, Glenn (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Mecom, John (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - Moers, Clifford (Box 28, Folder 6)
      - Muir, Andrew Forest (Box 28, Folder 7)
      - Noble, A.W. (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - Porter, W. S. (O. Henry) (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - Quinn, Bishop Clinton S. (Box 28, Folder 10)
      - Rice, William Marsh (Box 28, Folder 11)
      - Schiwetz, E. M. (Buck) (Box 28, Folder 12)
      - Sharp (Walter B.) Family (Box 28, Folder 13)
      - Smith, R.E. (Box 28, Folder 14)
      - Sterling, Ross (Box 28, Folder 15)
      - Strake, George W. (Box 28, Folder 16)
      - Welch, Robert A. (Box 28, Folder 17)
      - Welch, Louie (Box 28, Folder 18)
      - West (J.M. Sr.) Family (Box 28, Folder 19)
      - Weiss (Harry C) Family (Box 28, Folder 20)
      - Wortham, Gus (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - Subject Files (Box 29)
      - Airports/Air Travel (Box 29, Folder 1)
      - Alaska Statehood/Texas (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - Architecture (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - Art (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - Auditoriums (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - Aviation (Box 29, Folder 6)
      - Banks (Box 29, Folder 7)
      - Baseball (Box 29, Folder 8)
      - Bayous (Box 29, Folder 9)
      - Houston: Land of the Big Rich (Box 29, Folder 10)
      - Houston: Land of the Big Rich (Box 29, Folder 11)
      - Boating (Box 29, Folder 12)
      - Books - Houston in (Box 30, Folder 1)
      - Books - Houston in (Box 30, Folder 2)
      - Books - Houston in (Box 30, Folder 3)
      - Buildings (Box 30, Folder 4)
      - Businesses/Firms (Box 30, Folder 5)
      - Catholic Church (Box 30, Folder 6)
      - City, The (Box 30, Folder 7)
      - City, The (Box 30, Folder 8)
      - City, The (Box 30, Folder 9)
      - Clubs, Societies & Orgs (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - Controversy; The Liberal Mind/Other (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - Conventions / American Federation of Labor, 1938 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - Cotton/Anderson, Clayton & Co. (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - Criticisms (Box 31, Folder 5)
      - Culture/Miscellany (Box 31, Folder 6)
      - Directory/Houston (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - Downtown Area (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - Britannica Houston Article (Box 31, Folder 9)
      - Episcopal Church (Box 31, Folder 10)
      - Ethnic Groups (Box 31, Folder 11)
      - Fat Stock Show/Rodeo (Box 31, Folder 12)
      - Fire Department/Fires (Box 31, Folder 13)
      - Foley's (Box 31, Folder 14)
      - Galveston (Box 31, Folder 15)
      - “Giant”, Book and Film (Box 31, Folder 16)
      - Gold Mine 1908 (Box 31, Folder 17)
      - Gulf Freeway (Box 31, Folder 18)
      - Harris County (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - Harrisburg (Box 32, Folder 2)
      - Historical Sites (Box 32, Folder 3)
      - Historical Assoc./Houston (Box 32, Folder 4)
      - Holiday Celebrations/Early (Box 32, Folder 5)
      - History I (Box 32, Folder 6)
      - History II (Box 32, Folder 7)
      - History III (Box 32, Folder 8)
      - History IV (Box 32, Folder 9)
      - History V (Box 32, Folder 10)
      - Hospitals (Box 32, Folder 11)
      - Hotels (Box 32, Folder 12)
      - Houses (Box 32, Folder 13)
      - Houston Club (Box 32, Folder 14)
      - Houston Post 1 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - Houston Post 2 (Box 33, Folder 2)
      - Houston Post, History 1 (Box 33, Folder 3)
      - Houston Post, History 2 (Box 33, Folder 4)
      - Houston Post, History 3 (Box 33, Folder 5)
      - Houston Post essay by Mrs. Lane (Box 33, Folder 6)
      - Houston Lighting & Power Co. (Box 33, Folder 7)
      - Houston Telegraph/Cushing (Box 33, Folder 8)
      - Humble Building (Box 33, Folder 9)
      - Humble Oil & Refining Co. (Box 33, Folder 10)
      - Land: Facts & Fables (Box 33, Folder 11)
      - Libraries (Box 33, Folder 12)
      - Millionth Citizen Day (7/3/1954) (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Main Street (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Market House, City (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Market Square, Old (Box 34, Folder 4)
      - Mayors (other Public Officers) (Box 34, Folder 5)
      - Medical Center, Texas (Box 34, Folder 6)
      - Medical Societies (Box 34, Folder 7)
      - Mementos & Miscellany (Box 34, Folder 8)
      - Miscellany 1 (Box 34, Folder 9)
      - Miscellany 2 (Box 34, Folder 10)
      - Motoring & Early License Plates (Box 35, Folder 1)
      - Museums, Art Galleries & Painters (Box 35, Folder 2)
      - Museum of Natural History (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - Music General (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - Name Origins (streets, bayous, etc.) (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - NASA (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - National Dem. Convention 1928 (Box 35, Folder 7)
      - Newspapers, Periodicals (Box 35, Folder 8)
      - NO-TSU-OH Carnival (Box 35, Folder 9)
      - Oil (Box 35, Folder 10)
      - Parks, Fairs and Festivals (Box 35, Folder 11)
      - Periodicals - Houston Articles (Box 35, Folder 12)
      - Periodicals - Houston Articles (Box 36, Folder 1)
      - Periodicals - Houston Articles (Box 36, Folder 2)
      - Philanthropy (Box 36, Folder 3)
      - Police Department (Box 36, Folder 4)
      - Population Data (U.S. Census) (Box 36, Folder 5)
      - Political Activities (Box 36, Folder 6)
      - Port & Ship Channel-1 (Box 36, Folder 7)
      - Port & Ship Channel-2 (Box 36, Folder 8)
      - “Post Cards” of Houston (Box 36, Folder 9)
      - “Post Cards” of Houston (Box 36, Folder 10)
      - “Post Cards” of Houston (Box 36, Folder 11)
      - Post Office, U.S. (Box 36, Folder 12)
      - Railroads (Box 37, Folder 1)
      - Religion / Churches (Box 37, Folder 2)
      - Republic of Texas (Box 37, Folder 3)
      - Restaurants (Box 37, Folder 4)
      - Rice University (Box 37, Folder 5)
      - Rothko Chapel (Box 37, Folder 6)
      - San Jacinto / Battleship Texas (Box 37, Folder 7)
      - Schlueter Photography (Box 37, Folder 8)
      - Schools / Houston Public (Box 37, Folder 9)
      - Seal, City of Houston (Box 37, Folder 10)
      - Shamrock Hotel (Box 37, Folder 11)
      - Sketches of Houston/Kroll (Box 37, Folder 12)
      - Slums (Box 37, Folder 13)
      - Society (Box 37, Folder 14)
      - Song and Verse (Box 38, Folder 1)
      - Song and Verse (Box 38, Folder 2)
      - Stadiums (Box 38, Folder 3)
      - Subdivisions (brochures, etc.) (Box 38, Folder 4)
      - Suburbs (Box 38, Folder 5)
      - Suburbs/Baytown (Box 38, Folder 6)
      - Suburbs/Bellaire (Box 38, Folder 7)
      - Suburbs/Pasadena (Box 38, Folder 8)
      - Suburbs/West University Place (Box 38, Folder 10)
      - Suburbs/other (Box 38, Folder 11)
      - Texas Commerce Plaza (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Theaters (Box 39, Folder 2)
      - Transportation (Box 39, Folder 3)
      - University of Houston (Box 39, Folder 4)
      - University of St. Thomas (Box 39, Folder 5)
      - Weather Phenomena, Local (Box 39, Folder 6)
      - World War I (Box 39, Folder 7)
      - Yacht Clubs (Box 39, Folder 8)
      - Zoning & Houston Commission on (Box 39, Folder 9)
      - Zoo (Box 39, Folder 10)
- II. George Fuermann Professional Papers, 1952-2001, 11 Series
  This small sub-group consists of 11 series in 3 boxes. It includes biographical information, professional correspondence, information about the above described Historical Collecton, typescripts of Fuermann articles and books, dust jackets and pictorial proofs, as well as notes and collected photographs for a planned but unpublished volume, This is Houston. Of most interest in this sub-group, perhaps, is a selection of Fuermann typescripts with editing and accompanying letters in the hand of both J. Frank Dobie and Walter Prescott Webb.
  - A. Biographical/Bibliographic Information, 6 items (Box 40)
    - Biographical and Bibliographic Information., 1958-2001; 6 items (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - B. Correspondence, 15 items (Box 40)
    - Assorted Letters to George Fuermann., 1952-1960; 9 items (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Christmas Cards [to and from colleagues]., 1955-19?; 6 items (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - C. Fuermann Collection, 60 items (Box 40)
    - Fuermann Collection Information., 1964-1996; 15 items (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - Fuermann Collection at the Humble Building., 1963-1970; 45 items (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - D. Fuermann Articles, 21 items (Box 40)
    - “Post Card” Column Typescripts., 1953-1969; 6 items (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Assorted Published Articles by Fuermann., 1955-1973; 5 items (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - "Christmas in Houston", Typescript., 1963; 1 item (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - "Early Architecture in Houston", Typescript.[undated], 1 item (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - "Early Motoring in Houston", Typescript.[undated], 1 item (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - "Houston, 1880-1910", Southwest Historical Quarterly,1967, 1 item (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - "Houston Deplored", Typescript.[undated], 1 item (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - Houston Municipal Art Commission's Annual Report1965-1966, 1 item (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - "Houston in Song and Verse", Typescript. 1967, 1 item (Box 40, Folder 14)
    - "Noel in Houston", Typescript.1967, 1 item (Box 40, Folder 15)
    - "O. Henry in Houston", Typescript. [undated], 1 item (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - "Texas" for Encyclopedia Britanica[undated], 1 item (Box 40, Folder 17)
  - E. The Face of Houston, book., 1 item (Box 40)
    - The Face of Houston Typescript1963, 1 item. (Box 40, Folder 18)
  - F. Houston: The Feast Years, book., 4 items (Box 40)
    - Houston: The Feast Years Typescript1962, 1 item. (Box 40, Folder 19)
    - Houston: The Feast Years Paste-up page proofs1962, 1 item. (Box 40, Folder 20)
    - Houston: The Feast Years Galley Proofs1962, 1 item. (Box 40, Folder 21)
    - Letter from J. Frank Dobie about Houston: The Feast Years1962, 1 item. (Box 40, Folder 22)
  - G. Houston: Land of the Big Rich, book., 4 items (Box 40)
    - Houston: Land of the Big Rich Typescript1951, 1 item. (Box 40, Folder 23-25)
    - Houston: Land of the Big Rich Index- Typescript1951, 1 item. (Box 40, Folder 26)
  - H. Houston: The Once and Future City, book., 3 items (Box 41)
    - Houston: The Once and Future City Typescript1971, 1 item. (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Houston: The Once and Future City Blueline Proof1971, 1 item. (Box 41, Folder 2-3)
    - Houston: The Once and Future City Galley Proof1971, 1 item. (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - I. Reluctant Empire, book., 40 items (Box 41)
    - Reluctant Empire Review., 1957; 3 items. (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Letter from Roy Bedichek., [undated]; 1 item. (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Reluctant Empire Typescript of Chapters 1-8, with editing by J. Frank Dobie., 1956; 8 items (Box 41, Folder 7-8)
    - Correspondence with J. Frank Dobie., 1952-1956; 8 items (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Reluctant Empire Typescript of Chapters 1-3, with editing by Walter Prescott Webb., 1956; 3 items (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Letters from Walter Prescott Webb., 1956-1957; 5 items (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Reluctant Empire Galley Proof., 1957; 1 item (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Reluctant Empire Galley Proof., 1957; 1 item (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - Reluctant Empire Outline., 1957; 1 item (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Reluctant Empire List of Schweitz Drawings., 1957; 1 item (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Reluctant Empire Typescript Part 1 "The Mind of Texas"., 1957; 1 item (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Reluctant Empire Typescript Part 2 "Oil"., 1957; 1 item (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Reluctant Empire Typescript Part 3 "Metamorphosis"., 1957; 1 item (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Reluctant Empire Typescript Part 3 "Pride and Prejudice"., 1957; 1 item (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Reluctant Empire Typescript Part 3 "Texas Is Its Own Reward"., 1957; 1 item (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Letter from Lee Barker, Doubleday Executive Editor, 1957; 1 item (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - J. Other Fuermann Books (Box OVS 1)
    - Assorted Dust Jackets, Dust Jacket Proofs and Pictorial Page Proofs., 1957-1963; 17 items (Box OVS 1, Folder 38)
  - K. Planned Photographic Volume, This is Houston., 45 items (Box 42)
    - “Post Card” Column Regarding Planned Volume This is Houston [never published]., 1955; 1 item (Box 42, Folder 9)
    - Typescript Notes on Proposed Volume, This is Houston [never published]., c. 1956; 26 items (Box 42, Folder 10)
    - Assorted Letters from readers with solicited identification information for This is Houston., 1955-1957; 6 items (Box 42, Folder 11)
    - Item list of Assorted Photos assembled for This is Houston (Box 42, Folder 12)
      (See Sub-Group I, Series C, Boxes 18-21)